בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is ס"ט Samech Tet 69.
We pick up with the משנה, mishna, sorry, actually a little bit
ahead,
and you know, we are continuing, we sort of are dealing with
a mixture of things. We dealt with ישוב yeshuv about earning wages,
we dealt with issues about mixtures, we're going to get back to
issues about mixtures, but now we're also getting to, like, a different
area of כשרות, kashrus, one that is about being able to trust
somebody and not be constant supervision and to make sure that things
are being handled properly. So let's take a look at the משנה.
mishna. עובד כוכבים שהיה מעביר עם ישראל כדי יין ממקום למקום. Oved
kokhavim she-hayah ma'avir im yisrael kadei yayin mimakom lemakom.
So you had a non-Jew that was transporting barrels of wine owned
by a Jew and you wanted to make sure that the non-Jew
didn't touch them, touch the wine, or didn't, you know, exchange it
for his own wine. אם היה בחזקת המשתמר, Im hayah be-chezkas ha-mishtamer,
if you could be, if they're in a case where there is
a situation where there's a presumption that they're being guarded, we'll see
what that means in the גמרא, gemara, מותר, mutar, then it's permissible,
meaning that a Jew is keeping his eye on it. אם הודיעו
שהוא מפליג, Im hodio she-hu maflig, but if the Jew said to
the non-Jew, you know, I have to go somewhere for about an
hour, I'll be back in an hour, so the non-Jew felt that
he, nobody had an eye on him for the next hour. Okay,
so that seems to be the contrast to חזקת המשתמר. chezkas ha-mishtamer.
חזקת המשתמר Chezkas ha-mishtamer might mean, and that's going to be clearer
in the continuation in the משנה, mishna, might mean that the Jew
stepped away but he didn't say I'm going to be away for
an hour. So even though the Jew is not immediately present, he
could show up at any minute as opposed to this case where
the Jew made it clear that he was going to be away
for a period of time. So then if it is כדי שיסתום
ויסטום, kedei she-yistom ve-yistom, same word, whatever, one with a ש, sin,
one with a ס, samech, but they mean different things. יסתום Yistom
here means that he should puncture the lid and then, you know,
put a straw in and drink some or, you know, siphon off
some of the wine and maybe swap it with other wine or
something of that nature, or put water in its place, and then
reseal the hole, ויגוב, ve-yigov, and then the seal will dry like
you would replaster the hole and then it would dry, then it
would be a problem if it's that amount of time because then
if he's not afraid that the Jew's going to pop in then
he feels he's got the safety to do what he wants. So
as long as he can do, feel that he can siphon off
some wine and get away with it and nobody will detect him,
you have to be afraid that that's what he did. That's what
the תנא קמא tanna kamma says and therefore the wine is forbidden.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר כדי שיפתח את החבית ויגוב ויתנגב.
Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel omer kedei she-yiftach es ha-chavis ve-yigov ve-yisnagov. No, we're not afraid
he'll make a hole, that will always be detectable. We'll see why
in the גמרא. gemara. Well, so the only thing to be afraid
of is something that would take more time, that he would actually
completely remove the cover and apparently this was done in a way
that if you remove the cover you couldn't just reseal it, you
had to make a replacement cover. So that he would remove the
cover, ויגוב, ve-yigov, and reseal it, the way at least רש"י Rashi
explains it means by making a new cover and resealing it, and
then let the plaster dry, so that takes even more time than
making the hole and filling up the hole. Okay, and now the
other two cases in the משנה mishna are going to be almost
the identical cases and it's going to be, גמרא's gemara going to
ask why we need all of them.
המניח יינו בקרון
או בספינה, Ha-meniach yeino be-karon o be-sefinah, so there you are
and rather than having the non-Jew being the שלעפער, schlepper, I mean
he is the שלעפער schlepper here but not on its back, you're
going in a covered wagon okay or on a boat, והלך לו
בקפנדריא, ve-halach lo be-kapandarya, and then you took a shortcut. You left
the wagon or maybe the boat is docked or something,
ונכנס למדינה ורחץ, ve-nichnas limedinah ve-rachatz, and you took a little detour
from where the wagon was and you were passing by a town
and you wanted to take in a nice bath, okay, and you
left him alone in the wagon or on the boat.
So מותר, mutar, it's permissible even though you're doing something that's going
to take time because he doesn't know that you're going to be
away for a specific amount of time and you could always pop
back in. However, אם הודיעו שהוא מפליג, im hodio she-hu maflig, if
he said I'm going to be away for an hour to go
take a bath, okay, presumably you don't have to exactly say an
hour but if you didn't tell him why you're leaving, you just
said I'm going to step, you know, I gotta go take care
of an errand, I'll be right back, so then you could take
two hours but you say, you know, he thinks you could be
back at any minute. But if you told him I'm going to
be away for two hours then as long as he, so he
feels secure to do what he wants to do without you popping
back in. So if there's enough
time כדי שיסתום ויסטום ויגוב, kedei she-yistom ve-yistom ve-yigov, then it's forbidden
to make, to for him to puncture it and seal the hole.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel has some of the
opposite meaning. I know it's very interesting, right? Okay, it's like לשרש,
lesharesh, does that mean to put forth roots or to uproot? רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל אומר כדי שיפתח את החבית ויגוב ויתנגב. Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel omer kedei she-yiftach es ha-chavis ve-yigov ve-yisnagov. רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel again says no we're not afraid he'll
do that, that'll be discernible, we're only afraid that he will actually
complete... completely remove the cover and then replace it, reseal it, and
then that will dry. Third case. היה אוכלימו על השול. Haya ochelimo
al hashul. I'm sorry, third case. המניח עובד כוכבים בחנות. Haminuach oved
kochavim bachanat. You leave him in the store, he's your storekeeper, or
I don't know, maybe he's a customer. Okay, אף על פי שיצא
ונכנס מותר. Af al pi sheyatza venichnas mutar. Even though you leave
and you're coming back in, it's permissible because you didn't tell him
you're away for a particular time. Notice by the way the phrase
there of יוצא ונכנס. yotzei venichnas.
That is the classic phrase we have for a certain type of
a משגיח mashgiach
that's not a משגיח תמידי, mashgiach temidi, he's not there at all
times constantly supervising. As long as he's popping in and out, okay,
that's enough because the person is going to be on their toes
because they're afraid that you know you never know when the guy
is going to drop in and therefore you always have to be
you always have to be careful. Somebody once made an made an
interesting point that it's not נכנס ויוצא nichnas veyotzei but it's יוצא
ונכנס, yotzei venichnas, which basically means you're fundamentally there but occasionally you
go out as opposed to our contemporary interpretation of יוצא ונכנס yotzei
venichnas means somebody who pops in once every week or something at
some random time. What's even worse is when it's not even a
random time, when it's a scheduled time, right? That whole point here
is that somebody could be popping in at any moment. Okay, then
it's מותר. mutar. ואם הודיעו שהוא מפליג, Veim hodio shehu maflig, but
if you say I'm going out for a bit, okay, then כדי
שיסתום ויסתום ויגוף, kedei sheyistom veyistom veyigof, then if you're away for
that amount of time to make the hole and to seal it,
it's a problem. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר כדי שיפתח את החבית
ויגופיה ויחזור ותיגוף. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer kedei sheyiftach et hachavit
veyigafeiha veyachzor vetigof. So it's so funny, we need why do we
need to tell me three separate cases? There are I mean even
if there's a חידוש chidush of each one, why don't you just
list all three scenarios and then say the debate? But anyway, okay,
these were these were all the cases, it's basically all the same
debate. היה אוכל עמו על השולחן. Haya ochel imo al hashulchan. Now
let's say you invited the non-Jew to eat with you at your
table and you're serving non-מבושל mevushal wine. But you know, he is
you know, you're pouring the wine for him. You're not afraid that
he's touching it or that he's pouring it.
By the way, I just think it's fascinating that the משנה Mishna
is even describing that scenario, that there you are with a non-Jew
drinking wine at the same table. We're going to have an even
more shocking scenario at the end of today's דף. daf. Anyway, so
in that case, והניח לגינים על השולחן, vehiniach leginim al hashulchan, and
you left certain like you know like carafes on the שולחן, shulchan,
ולגין על הדולבקי, velagin al hadulbeki, and one also on the דולבקי,
dulbeki, which is basically like a type of a I don't know
like a
like a what do you call it like a server or something,
like some type of a how do they translate it? Does anybody
have an English there? No, nobody has an English. Amazing, everybody's using
דף daf without an English. Anyway, so it's some type of a
like of a like of a wine stand or something. It's not
directly on the table. Okay, so in that case,
והניחו ויצא, vehiniacho veyatza, and you said somebody I just got I
got to run out, I'll be right back. מה שעל השולחן אסור.
Ma sheal hashulchan assur. What's on the table is forbidden. Now in
this case, right, even though it's immediately forbidden, even if you didn't
say that you were מפליג. maflig. Why is that? So, right, before,
if you didn't tell him that you were going to be away
for a certain period of time, it's all okay, you're not afraid
he touched. But here there's two reasons why it's immediately forbidden even
if you didn't tell him that you were going to that you
were going to be away for a certain amount of time. One
is he's drinking with you at the table, so he's already drinking
the wine and he feels a certain amount of freedom. The other
thing is תוספות Tosafot points out is that presumably the wine bottles
are already open, right? In the other cases, the barrels were closed.
So in this case, since he's already there and he's drinking with
permission and it's just and it's not even having to open a
seal or anything like that, it's just touching an open barrel of
wine, there even if he's afraid you'll pop in at any moment,
he feels he why he feels a certain amount of freedom, so
it's forbidden. Okay,
so therefore in that case, מה שעל השולחן אסור, ma sheal hashulchan
assur, שעל הדולבקי מותר. sheal hadulbeki mutar. What's on the דולבקי, dulbeki,
did you look it up? How'd they translate it? Cupboard.
Cupboard. Yeah, I guess so. תוספות Tosafot in my Hebrew is a
counter, so maybe.
Oh really? All right, so that's what I said. Some type of
a some type of a wine stand, a cupboard. Anyway, what's in
the cupboard is permissible because again, since you might pop back in
and what's and he doesn't feel freedom to be with to take
what's in the cupboard, so that's like what we've been teaching before.
So the חידוש chidush here though is that what's on the table
is immediately forbidden.
ואם אמר לו הוי מוזג ושותה, Veim amar lo hoy mozeg veshoteh,
but if you said to him, presumably while you were there at
the table, not as you were leaving, I think, but while you
were at the table, you know, go ahead, pour for yourself, drink
etc. which is pretty surprising. What are you doing telling him to
to pour and drink? It's going to make the wine forbidden. I
don't know, maybe you maybe you figure the battle you gave him,
you told him that he could go ahead and help himself to
he
handed the bottle.
I guess. Anyway, but if you said some type of encouraging words
like that which gave him an even sense of greater freedom to
take from the wine, you know, help yourself, make yourself at home,
in that case, אף של דולבקי אסור, af shel dulbeki assur, even
though you leave him without telling him that you're going to be
away for a certain period of time, once you said make yourself
at home, he'll make himself a home, so it's forbidden. So even
if he thinks you're coming back in the next minute, you know,
you said "Make yourself at home," so he's going to take it
from the cupboard, from the cupboard. חביתא דצורי, Chavita d'Tzuri,
now that's in terms of like the carafe, which is basically open
and easily accessible and he feels a certain amount of freedom with
etc. However,
חביות פתוחות אסורות, chaviyot petuchot asurot, if it's the barrels, okay, that's
a different story. So if it's an open barrel, similarly, that's going
to be a problem, because you said make yourself at home. But
if it's סתומות מותרות, stumot mutarot, but if it's the sealed barrels,
then even if you said make yourself at home and the whole
thing, those are going to be those sealed barrels he doesn't feel
that he has that freedom with, okay, and those are going to
remain permissible,
even if you told him even if you told him you were
leaving for a while, but it'll become a problem כדי שיפתח ויגוף
ותיגוב kedei sheyiftach v'yagof v'tigov again if it's the amount of time
that he could completely remove the cover and reseal it etc. That
gets back to that normal הלכה, halacha, okay? Okay.
So basically, those are that's the story in that case, in that
case where he's already drinking at your table, even if he's afraid
you might pop back in, open stuff is, the open stuff on
the table is forbidden and even the stuff that's in the cupboard
is going to be forbidden if you said to him things like
"make yourself at home," even in cases where he feels you might
pop back in. Okay, so that's an exceptional case.
No, anytime it says forbidden, thank you for asking that. Anytime it
says forbidden, we're assuming forbidden בהנאה, be'hana'ah, right, because it basically means
we're afraid he touched it or something of that nature. היכי דמי
בחזקת המשתמר? Heichi dami b'chezkat hamishtamer? In the משנה, Mishna, the משנה
Mishna contrasted telling him you're going to be away
for a while and חזקת משתמר. chezkat mishtamer. So the simple read
is: חזקת משתמר chezkat mishtamer is just not telling him you'll be
away for a while, that he's afraid you might pop back in
any minute. But because it's described it as חזקת משתמר, chezkat mishtamer,
it sounds like it's possibly even a higher level of שימור. shimur.
So what exactly is that case in the משנה? Mishna? So כדתניא,
k'detanya, like we taught in a ברייתא: Beraita: הרי שהיו חמריו ופועליו
טעונים טהרות אפילו הפליג מהן יתר ממיל טהרותיו טהורות. Harei shehayu chamrav
u'foalav te'unim taharot afilu hiflig mehen yeter mi'mil taharotav tehorot. Let's say
your workers were carrying,
so this is a similar concern. It's not a concern of non-Jews
and wine, it's a concern about workers that are עמי הארץ amei
ha'aretz and they'll touch your טהור tahor fruit or wine or whatever
if you're not being on top of them and you're not keeping
your eye on them, okay.
So there they were, what, with no cameras?
Right. There they were, they were schlepping it, okay. So if you
go ahead and leave them, even if it's more than a מיל,
mil, which is whatever, a kilometer, like 18 minutes, 20 minutes or
something like that, you didn't tell them that you're going to be
away. You might be popping back any minute, similar to what we've
been discussing. So
טהורות, tahorot, they're טהור tahor because again they're afraid you could pop
back any minute, they'll be on their best care.
מיל Mil is a thousand steps. Right.
מיל Mil is, א מיל a mil is two thousand אמות. amot.
Okay, so it's about, it's about a kilometer.
Okay. ואם אמר להם לכו ואני בא אחריכם, Ve'im amar lahem lechu
v'ani ba achareichem, if however you say, "Go on ahead, I'll catch
up with you." So I'll catch up with you means that you're
going to be, that they have some time to themselves, they're not
afraid you're going to drop in at any second. Then כיון שנתעלמה
עינו מהם, keivan shenitalma eino mehem, the moment that you are no
longer, they're no longer within sight, טהורותיו טמאות, taharotav tameot, you have
to feel that they're going to be sloppy and they'll touch your
stuff and it'll be טמא. tame. Now, now that doesn't help, I
mean, that doesn't give any greater clarity than the משנה. Mishna. That's
like if you say you'll be back at any, you know, if
you don't tell them give them indication that they've got time to
themselves, then it's okay, and if there's an indication that there's a
period that they're going to be unsupervised, it's a problem. But now
the גמרא Gemara queries this. It
says מאי שנא רישא ומאי שנא סיפא? mai shna reisha u'mai shna
seifa? What's the difference between the רישא reisha and the סיפא? seifa?
Now the obvious answer is: what do you mean what's the difference?
The difference is in the סיפא seifa he said, "Go, go, go
on ahead, I'll catch up to you." But the question is, the
way רש"י Rashi sort of and תוספות Tosafot explain it, is that
we're assuming
that we're dealing with a case that the barrels are open. We're
not specifically dealing with closed barrels. The evidence that we're not specifically
dealing with closed barrels is, if we were dealing with closed barrels,
then even if you said "Go and I'll catch up to you",
it should only be a problem in the amount of time it
would take them to open the barrel, right, like our משנה? Mishna?
Remember in our משנה, Mishna, even if you told them "Go, I'll
be away for an hour", it only is a problem if you
leave them long enough that they can either make a hole in
the top of the barrel or remove the top or whatever? Here
it says as soon as you lose sight of them, it's immediately
forbidden. Right, everybody hear that difference? So the fact that it says
it's immediately forbidden, it doesn't even say the time it takes them
to make a hole in the barrel, indicates, says תוספות, Tosafot, that
we're talking about open barrels of wine.
They just touch any of the wine, the whole barrel is טמא?
tame? Yeah.
So there's no בטל בשישים batel b'shishim or?
No, because the touch is on. If they touch something and then
it poured it into that, that would be ביטול, bitul, but if...
If you touched it, it's the touch touched all the wine at
once. It's considered like you touched everything. So all the wine in
the barrel.
So okay, so everybody get the idea that it says here when
it's a problem, it says immediately it's a problem. It doesn't say
the time it takes to remove the top. So תוספות Tosafot says
that seems to be the indicator that it's uncovered. So if it's
uncovered, what the גמרא Gemara says is I don't get it. If
it's uncovered,
then even if you know, even if you didn't say like, like,
like I'll catch up later, if it's uncovered it takes two seconds
for them to touch it. So even if you're, you know, even
if you're a little bit away from them, and even if they're
afraid you might show any second, it should be like the case
of leaving the guy at the table. Remember the last case of
the משנה, Mishna, leaving the guy at the table? That if it's
uncovered, then it should be immediately a problem even if they're afraid
you'll pop back in. So מאי שנא רישא ומאי שנא סיפא? Mai
shna reisha u-mai shna seifa? If it genuinely is a case of
uncovered, it should be a problem even in the first case. So
אמר רב יצחק רישא במטהרי חמר ופועליו לכך. Amar Rav Yitzchak: reisha
b-metaharei chammar ve-po’alav lekach. No,
the first case is that since you knew they were going to
be schlepping your barrels of uncovered wine, and you first made them
all go to the מקוה mikvah first. Okay. All right, well if
that's true, then the obvious question is then who cares, then it
should always be okay even in the סיפא seifa if they're טהור.
tahor. אי הכי סיפא נמי? I hachi seifa nami? So in the
סיפא seifa also, even if you told them I'll catch up, it
should be okay, they're all טהור. tahor. No. אין עם הארץ מקפיד
על מגע חבירו. Ein am ha-aretz makpid al maga chavero. No, since
they're עם הארץ, am ha-aretz, they're טהור, tahor, but they're not going
to mind if their friend comes and you know and touches it.
So that's what you have to be afraid of, okay? And therefore
if you say I'll catch up, you have to be afraid that
a friend might drop by. אי הכי I hachi says the גמרא,
Gemara, if you're afraid a friend will drop by even in the
first case, okay, even if you're just, even if you didn't tell
them I'll catch up, once they're no longer in your sight you
have to be afraid. So that a friend might drop by.
נמי נימא הכי? Nami nima hachi? So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, דבא
להו דרך אלכסון. de-ba lehu derech al-achlasson. No, the you're right, you
know, it only takes a second for their non-טהור tahor friend to
touch it, but because you didn't tell them I'll catch up later,
they will be afraid that you'll be able to cut like, you
know, to do a shortcut and to pop back in. So yes,
you're not there, okay? This basically is just a way of explaining
what's going on in our משנה. Mishna. In our משנה, Mishna, when
you did not say I'll be away for an hour, you just
said I gotta, you know, I gotta step out for a minute.
But right? So as long as there's a possibility you could pop
back in at any second, that's called חזקת משתמר. Chezkas Mishtamer. Okay,
so here what's the possibility? You're on a road, they got 20
minutes ahead of you, okay? Even though you didn't say anything, why
don't they feel confident that you're not being supervised? So the answer
is it doesn't matter that they're 20 minutes ahead of you if
they're there would be a possibility or at least they're afraid that
there's a possibility that you could take a shortcut and pop back
in without knowing them. Okay, so that's חזקת משתמר. Chezkas Mishtamer. Even
though they know you're away, if they're afraid that you could pop
in at any second, they don't know how long you're away for,
they think you might have only stepped out for ten seconds, or
maybe they do know that
you're away, that you went five blocks away, but they're afraid that
you can take a shortcut and be back in any moment. So
that's called חזקת משתמר. Chezkas Mishtamer. It's a combination of not telling
them that you're going to be away for a certain period of
time and the possibility that you could that you could pop back
in at any moment without without without warning. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says אי הכי סיפא נמי? I hachi seifa nami? So if
that's true in the end they should be afraid about that as
well. So here finally no, here's what when you tell them you'll
be away for a period of time, they feel secure. כיון דאמר
להו לכו ואני בא אחריכם סמכא
דעתייהו. Keivan de-amar lehu lechu va-ani ba achareichem samcha da'atayhu. Since you
say I'll catch up, it means you're not expecting to surprise them
and all of a sudden you know take a shortcut and be
back there suddenly. Okay, so bottom line it just explains the משנה,
Mishna, which is if you don't tell them how that you're going
to be away for X period of time and they they have
a reason to think you could pop back in in any minute
then it's okay. But if, I mean imagine a case you didn't
tell them you're going to be away for a period of time,
but let's say by circumstances it's clear. Like you said, oh yeah
I'm going to go to the I'm going to go take a
bath. And they know that the bathhouse is a is a one
hour trip in each direction. You don't have to say out of
your words the amount of time. But the point is in a
scenario where they'd be concerned that you could drop in back in
at any second, you're good. If however because of what you said
or because of the circumstances they're confident you'll be away for a
certain period of time, then if it's an open barrel, like the
case of the table right or whatever like the last case of
the משנה Mishna and so on, okay, then you know that would
be a
problem right away. But if it's not an open barrel, excuse me,
let me say that again.
If they're afraid you'll pop back in at any time, you're good.
If they're
not. If they're afraid, if they feel they have a certain period
of time without interruption,
then it goes by
the amount of time it would take to puncture and to reseal
etc. according to the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, according to רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel the amount of time it would take to remove the
whole cover and to reseal it. Okay, once they feel confident that
they have uninterrupted time. If it is however a case of one
second, a case of an open barrel, okay, you know,
then even if they're afraid you'll pop back in at any second,
like the case of the משנה, Mishnah, or like the case in
the end about the about eating at the table, if they feel
a certain degree of comfort even if they're afraid you'll pop back
in if it's open then it's forbidden immediately, that's the last case
of the משנה. Mishnah. But when it's closed, that's when these things
make a difference. Yes, you wanted to ask something?
You talked about
כפור הגוזר kfor ha-gozer to be reversible, these things being...
No, not the wine, only in right, correct.
The thing about the friend is a little strange because the others
are sort of like reasonable presumptions about what could happen given the
time, but if they're all טהור, tahor, like that doesn't seem to
be like a reasonable that there's some other guy's going to come
who is טמא, tamei, you know, and not like like then it
could be like any scenario, make up anything, you know.
But that remember the case in this case we just dealt with
as I said תוספות Tosfos inferred it was an open barrel. Once
it's an open barrel we're much more concerned, right? Even in the
case in where they're afraid you'll pop back in in any second,
we're concerned in a case of an open barrel. So you're right,
it is a but it is a little bit getting a little
far-fetched but that's the reality once you're dealing with something open. All
right. המניח עובדי כוכבים בחנותו המניח יין בקרונה ובספינה. Ha-maniach ohvei kochavim
b'chanuso ha-maniach yayin b'karono u'b'sefinah. Now we have all these various scenarios.
Okay, it's a closed barrel, if they're afraid you might pop back
in it's okay, if they're not afraid then it's a certain amount
of time. וצריכא, U'tzricha,
you need all three cases. דתנא עובדי כוכבים דסבר, De-tana ohvei kochavim
d'savor, if they said the first case that they were just schlepping
the barrels of wine, דסבר דילמא אתי וחזי ליה, d'savor dilma atei
v'chazei lei, there you could say that he's not going to do
anything if you haven't told him you'll be away for a period
of time, he's afraid you'll pop back in and you'll see him.
אבל בקרונה ובספינה אימא דמפליג ליה לספינתיה ועביד מאי דבעי, Aval b'karono
u'b'sefinah eima d'mafleg lei l'sefintai v'avid mai d'ba'i, but if it's a
case about a wagon or boat, he says look you're leaving the
boat, you're going into town, okay, so he feels he's got freedom.
It's not like you know you've just sort of like got a
little bit ahead on the trip. The time it takes to leave
the boat or whatever, somebody's really going to go do some some
whole major activity in town.
ואי תנא בקרונה ובספינה משום דסבר דילמא אתי באורחא אחריתי וקאי אגודא
וחזי ליה. Ve-i tana b'karono u'b'sefinah mishum d'savor dilma atei b'orcha achrisi
v'kai aguda v'chazei lei. Okay, but if it had just said that,
we would have explained that that case still we understand, okay, so
that case you would think you've always got a problem. קא משמע
לן Kamashma lan that if you don't give them a limited amount
specific amount of time, you're safe. Why are you safe? Because they'll
be afraid that even though you know they might think like I'll
hear him if he has to you know get back on the
boat, I'm totally safe. No, because maybe he could stand somewhere on
the dock with a pair of binoculars and see you. So that
case the חידוש chiddush is that there'd be a good reason to
think in the case of the ספינה sefinah it's always a problem
because he'll feel that he always has protection and he can always
do it without being discovered. קא משמע לן Kamashma lan that even
there he's afraid he'll be discovered if you haven't given him an
amount of time he's afraid you'll be at the dock and you'll
be looking at it. וקאי אגודא V'kai aguda you'll be at the
you'll be at the shore you know at whatever on the you
know
at the bridge וחזי ליה v'chazei lei and you'll see him. אבל
עובדי כוכבים בחנותו Aval ohvei kochavim b'chanuso but leaving him in your
store אימא אחלי לבבא ועביד כל דבעי eima achali l'bava v'avid kol
d'ba'i you might think there even if you didn't tell him you're
going to be away for a certain period of time you leave
him alone in the store he'll just lock the door. קא משמע
לן Kamashma lan you're not afraid of that. I guess because you'll
you'll assume that if he locks the door and you come and
you find the door locked you'll say what the heck were you
doing locking my the door to my store. So
so the חידוש chiddush is that in these scenarios even though a
guy might feel more secure even without you giving him an amount
of time, heck I'll hear him get back on the boat, heck
I'll be able to just close the door, I'll hear him open
the door to the store etc. the חידוש chiddush is that if
you didn't give him an amount of time he's still fearful enough
that you can surprise him or you'll catch him having locked the
door that that's enough to assume that he's not going to fool
around with your wine. And the only time it's a problem is
if you made it clear that you weren't going to be back
for a certain period of time.
Is it clear why he's fooling around with your wine like is
he trying to steal it or is he just a מטמא?
metamei? No, one of two possibilities. Either you're afraid he's trying to
pour it for עבודה זרה avoda zara which is a funny concern
but that seems to be like a dominant concern that we're afraid
that they are so
like you know focused on עבודה זרה avoda zara that
as soon
as they see wine
they think of עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Exactly. As soon as you
they see some un-watched wine it's one of the great opportunities to
offer this to my god. Or they're afraid that he'll want to...
Just, you know, steal some of it and add some water to
it or swap it with inferior wine and in the process he'll
touch it and he'll handle it.
What was it, a deliberate sabotage?
Right, it wasn't to make it אסור assur to you, correct.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now, that so
that's why that definitely that really is a חידוש chiddush in all
these cases, the fact that once you as long as you're not
clear that you'll be away for a certain amount of time, he's
considered you assume that he'll be afraid and everything is okay. Okay,
that definitely is a חידוש, chiddush, even in the case of the
boat and the store, and that's the הלכה. halacha. Now, if you
do say you'll be away an amount of time, it's a time
it takes to either make a hole and seal it or to
remove the cover and seal it. That's the debate. So now we're
going to see some specifics about that debate. אמר רבה בר בר
חנה אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbah Bar Bar Chana Amar Rabbi Yochanan
מחלוקת בשל סיד. machlokes beshel sid.
The debate of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel and
the חכמים Chachamim
is with a plaster top to the to the barrel. The barrel,
by the way, was made out of like pottery. Okay, plaster's white,
and the point being that when you make a hole in the
top of a plaster top and then you fill it again with
like plaster, it's the same color. And that's why the חכמים Chachamim
think that as long as there's just opportunity to fill the hole,
you're okay. All right, but אבל בשל טיט, aval beshel tit, if
it's made of like a type of a tar, which is black,
then דברי הכל כדי שיפתח ויגוף ויגוב, divrei hakol k’dei sheyiftach veyigof
veyigov, everybody would agree that we're not afraid he'll make a hole
because then the hole, I don't know why you can't fill the
hole with with טיט, tit, why you can only fill the hole
with plaster, but whatever the reason is, maybe it takes the טיט,
tit, maybe if it's טיט tit it gets dark over time or
something. Okay. What? No, their their barrels were made out of pottery.
תוספות Tosafot has a long discussion how this applies to wood barrels.
Okay, so if it's though a tar type of a top, everybody
agrees you're not afraid he'll make a hole because then it will
be discernable, and everybody agrees you have the longer amount of time
until actually to remove the whole top and replace the top.
Okay, so מיתיבי, meitivei, I'll ask you this. אמר רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל לחכמים, Amar Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel lachachamim, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel said to the חכמים, Chachamim, והלא סיתומו ניכר
בין מלמעלה בין מלמטה. vehalo situmo nikar bein milma’alah bein milmatah. But
if what where he will fill if you're saying you're afraid he'll
make a hole, I'm not afraid of that because the fill of
the hole will be obvious, whether above or below. So אי אמרת
בשל טיט מחלוקת, ei amart beshel tit machlokes, if their debate
is the case where the top of the barrel is made out
of tar, היינו דקתני סיתומו ניכר בין מלמעלה בין מלמטה, hainu d’katani
situmo nikar bein milma’alah bein milmatah, you'll be able to see where
it's filled,
because the fill will look like a whitish look and the and
the top itself will be black. אלא אי אמרת, Ela ei amart,
the bottom and top means the outside, meaning if this is the
if this is the cover of the barrel and you pierce a
hole through here, מלמעלה milma’alah is what you look at when you're
looking at the top of it, and מלמטה milmatah is the underneath
side of the top. Okay. בין מלמעלה בין Bein milma’alah bein okay.
אלא אי אמרת בשל
סיד מחלוקת, Ela ei amart beshel sid machlokes,
but if you say the debate is by a plaster top, בשלמא
מלמטה ידיע, bishlama milmatah yediyah, so below it'll be obvious, presumably because
the filling, when you fill the hole you made from the top
with plaster, it won't, you know, it won't totally seal the bottom,
there'll be like an air gap at the bottom, you know. I
mean, you would have to remove the top and, you know, smear
it over the bottom. Right, if you're just like dripping plaster into
here to seal it, it's not going to totally fill the, you
know, you'll see like a little gap at the bottom because you
didn't remove the actual thing and fill it and smear it over.
And it might also be a different color. And it might also
be a different color, exactly. It'll be whiter at the top, but
underneath where it's been in contact with wine, the other stuff is
dark and your stuff is whiter. Okay. So then he says like
this. So he said, אי אמרת בשל סיד מחלוקת, ei amart beshel
sid machlokes, where was I? So היינו ד, hainu d, okay, so
if it's plaster, if it's if it's what do you call it,
tar, that's why he's saying it's obvious at the top and the
bottom, and that's why he's challenging the position of the חכמים. Chachamim.
אלא אי אמרת בשל סיד מחלוקת, Ela ei amart beshel sid machlokes,
but if it's plaster, בשלמא מלמטה ידיע, bishlama milmatah yediyah, so okay,
he should be challenging them by saying the underneath is obvious, it's
a different color, it's not totally full. אלא למעלה הלא לא ידיע,
Ela lema’alah halo lo yediyah, but the top isn't obvious. So I
understand why you want to say the that they're talking about plaster
because it more explains the חכמים’s Chachamim position, that why they feel
that it you can get away with it. But רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel seems to feel that challenge the חכמים
Chachamim and say that it'll be obvious. So the גמרא Gemara says,
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל הוא דלא ידע מאי קאמרי רבנן. Rabban Shimon
Ben Gamliel hu d’lo yada mai ka’amri rabbanan. No, רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel didn't really understand which scenario the rabbis
were talking about. He didn't know whether they were talking about plaster
or tar. Okay. והכי קאמר להו, Ve’hachi ka’amar lehu,
here's what he's saying to them. אי בשל טיט קאמרתון, Ei beshel
tit ka’amritun, if you're talking about a case of tar, סיתומו ניכר
בין מלמעלה בין מלמטה, situmo nikar bein milma’alah bein milmatah, your position
makes no sense because it's obvious at the top and at the
bottom. And that's exactly why the claim is being made, the רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying that they're not saying their position by
tar, because it is obvious. Okay, so ואי בשל סיד קאמרתון, ve’ei
beshel sid ka’amritun, but even if you're saying by plaster, which is
exactly... What רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says they are saying, they're saying
it only in the plaster case. So he says, I would still
challenge it. ניהא דלמעלה לא ידיע, niha delemala lo yedia, I get
that at the top it's not obvious and that's why you think
that the guy can get away with it, but למטה מי לא
ידיע? lemata mi lo yedia? As soon as you open up the
cover and you look underneath, it will be obvious. Okay, so that's
why רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan wants to limit their debate to the
case of the plaster top, because at least then you can understand
why the חכמים Chachamim could think you could get away with it,
because at least from the surface it looks okay. And רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel would object to that. He's not
going to do it that way. He'll be afraid he'll get caught
out when they actually open the cover of the barrel. Okay, so
what would be the חכמים's Chachamim response to that? ורבנן, Ve-rabbanan, the
Rabbis would say back, כיון דלמעלה לא ידיע לא מסיק אדעתיה דאפיק
וחזי ליה. keivan delemala lo yedia lo massik adaateih de-appik ve-chazei leih.
Look, the guy really wants to steal some wine. He's not, you
know, he persuades himself or he doesn't think about the fact oh,
when they open the top and they look underneath they'll see that
I pierced a hole. No, you know, he figures they'll come, they'll
see everything looks normal, I'll get away with it. If they find,
you know, he doesn't even think that they'll find a hole a
week later, and if so, he figures by then, you know, whatever,
he'll have deniability. Okay, אינמי, inami, זימנין דחלים, zimnin de-chalim, and sometimes
actually it might actually do, you know, will get filled up at
the bottom and maybe you know, or who knows, by the time
that they discover it maybe it will start looking the right color.
Okay, so that's why רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that they're debating
the case of plaster because at least it can explain why according
to the חכמים, Chachamim, why the guy thinks he can get away
with it. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so now it's too bad Michael
isn't here because Michael always wants to know how we rule and
here the גמרא Gemara finally rules: הלכה כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל. halacha
ke-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. We actually rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל,
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, which actually is a מקל meikel ruling. We're
not afraid of piercing a hole, that'll be obvious, we're only afraid
of actually removing the top. הואיל ותנן סתמא כוותיה, hoil ve-tenan stama
kevatteih, and how do I know we rule that way? Because the
very end of the משנה Mishna ends with רבן שמעון בן גמליאל.
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. The end of the משנה Mishna that dealt
with the case of eating at the table, right, remember those cases
about eating at the table, etc. And then it dealt with the
case about you're there, you're more afraid that he's going to touch
stuff even if you didn't give him a time, but it says
at least those cases though, what's the sealed barrels, it does, it
is a minimum amount of time. And what's the minimum amount of
time by the sealed barrels?
דתנן, de-tenan, היה אוכל על השלחן עמו והניח לגין על השלחן לגין
על הדלפקי והניח ויצא מה שעל השלחן אסור ומה שעל הדלפקי מותר
ואם אמר לו
הוי מזוג ושותה אף שעל הדלפקי אסור. haya ochel al hashulchan imo
ve-hiniach lagin al hashulchan lagin al hadulfaki ve-hiniach ve-yatza ma she-al hashulchan
assur ve-ma she-al hadulfaki mutar ve-im amar lo hevei mazug ve-shoteh af
she-al hadulfaki assur. So if you leave him at the table then
any, all those open pitchers or whatever it's all going to be
a problem, especially if you tell him make yourself at home. But
חביות פתוחות אסורות, chaviyot petuchot assurot, and open, open barrels are forbidden,
וסתומות מותרות, u-stumot mutarot, sealed ones remain
permissible, כדי שיפתח ויגוף ותיגוב. kedei she-yiftach ve-yigof ve-tigov. And there it
only quotes the position of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel, the amount of time it would take to remove the top
and to remake it and to seal it. So it does not
say the position of the חכמים. Chachamim. So because the משנה Mishna
ends with the position of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel and says it in a סתם stam way, doesn't attribute it
specifically to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, you see
that that is the הלכה halachic position.
So the
גמרא Gemara says פשיטא. pishita. פשיטא, Pishita, so it's obvious we rule
like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, that's the סתם
stam end of the משנה. Mishna. What are you telling me? I
could also see it's the סתם stam end of the משנה. Mishna.
No, מהו דתימא כולה רבן שמעון בן גמליאל קתני לה. mahu deteima
kulla Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel katani lah. I might have thought that
that whole last case about drinking at the table was all a
continuation of the quote of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel. It wasn't the סתם משנה stam mishna פוסק paskening like רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, it was all part of
the, of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל's Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel last statement.
קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, that it is actually the סתם
משנה stam mishna ruling like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel. So now we have concluded that even if you leave a
non-Jew and give a non-Jew the amount of time it will take,
you know, he feels secure that you're not going to interrupt him,
it's only a problem if he has the time, we're not concerned
about making a hole, it's only a problem if he has the
amount of time to actually remove the whole top and place it
back on. So now the גמרא Gemara asks a very good and
important practical question, which is, why are we ever, why are we
ever concerned? Why? Let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this: וכי מאחר דקיימא לן כוותיה דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל, ve-chi
me-achar de-kaima lan kevatteih de-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, now you're telling me
we rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, that
the only thing we're concerned about is not piercing little holes but
actually removing the whole seal, the whole top. דלא חייש לסתומי, delo
chaish le-situmi, that
you're not afraid about making holes. Excuse me. וחזינא כוותיה דרבי אליעזר.
ve-chazina kevatteih de-Rabbi Eliezer.
Now we rule like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer way back in the
second פרק. perek. You might remember this, that there was a whole
debate about wine, whether wine you need, you need one seal or
two seals, whether you need חותם chotam or חותם בתוך חותם. chotam
betoch chotam. And the גמרא Gemara there ruled like רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer that you only need one seal. Now that was a little
bit, there was a huge תוספות Tosafot there and there's a huge
תוספות Tosafot here because on the one hand, that גמרא Gemara and
this גמרא Gemara says we rule like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that
you only need one seal, but there's all these other גמרות Gemaras
that sound like wine needs two seals. So how do you reconcile
them? So תוספות Tosafot does a lot of different attempts to reconcile.
I'll just tell you one simple way תוספות Tosafot reconciles it is,
is that the question is, are you going to be inspecting your
own seal? So if I go ahead and I leave my closed
barrel of wine with this non-Jew and then I'm going to come
back. Okay, I am the same I I know what that barrel
looked like. So in that case one seal might be enough because
there's a reasonable possibility that I'll see that it's tampered with. Okay,
but if I send the non-Jew to deliver my wine to Chanan,
how does one seal help? He doesn't know what it looked like
originally. So in that case I might need a double seal. So
that's how תוספות Tosfos tries to reconcile a number of גמרות Gemaras
that seem to rule like רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer that a single
seal is okay with other גמרות Gemaras that seem to rule that
you need a double seal. Okay, there's another problem also, which is
if I sell send it to Chanan that תוספות Tosfos deals with,
which is how do I know forget you know since he doesn't
even know like like I how maybe he completely took that entire
barrel of wine brought it into his house and replaced it with
a completely other barrel of wine with an untampered seal but it
was a completely different barrel. How does he even know forget how
does he know what the seal looked like how does he know
what the barrel looks like. Okay so תוספות Tosfos deals with some
of those realities. But anyway this גמרא Gemara and obviously this one's
a huge issue in תוספות. Tosfos. What type of protection did they
need for transporting barrels of wine to know that they weren't tampered
with. Okay but this גמרא Gemara says one minute this גמרא Gemara
says that according to רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer you okay you just
need a single seal and you you're confident it won't be tampered
with. So if that's true I could just always again let's let's
assume it's the same owner so I'll come back and I'll be
able to recognize it. So I should always be able to leave
my wine with a non-Jew right I should here's my sealed barrel
of wine I'm leaving it with a non-Jew I'm saying I'm going
to be away for 10 hours okay however long. So according to
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel we're not afraid that
he'll make a hole in the top we're only afraid he'll replace
the entire top. But we just got through saying that חותם אחד
chotam echad is enough that one seal is enough and I'll we're
confident enough that I'll be able to see if it was tampered
with. Okay or maybe רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
or the flip version of that is רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel isn't afraid that he'll tamper with a sealed barrel
of wine. So if we're not afraid that he'll make a hole
and we're not afraid that he'll tamper with a sealed barrel of
wine or if he does or or we're confident enough that I'll
notice if it's been tampered with why can't we just always leave
our wine with non-Jews our sealed barrels of wine with non-Jews. So
that's the גמרא's Gemara question. וכי מאחר דקיימא לן כוותיה דרבן שמעון
בן גמליאל דלא חיישינן לסתימה Veki achar dekaiman lan kevastei deRabban Shimon
ben Gamliel delo chaishinan lestituma והלכתא כוותיה דרבי אליעזר דלא חיישינן לזיופא
vehilchesa kevastei deRebbi Eliezer delo chaishinan leziyufa and he's not afraid of
forging a sealed a seal a sealed barrel of wine. השתא מאי
טעמא לא מספינן חמרא בידא דעובד כוכבים Hashta mai taama lo maspinan
chamra beyada deoveid kochavim why not just have the non-Jews keep the
keep a look on our wine what's there to be afraid of
as long as it's sealed. So the גמרא Gemara says משום שייכא
mishum sheika because of שייכא. sheika. Now what does שייכא sheika mean?
So רש"י Rashi says שייכא sheika means basically if you look at
רש"י Rashi three lines from the bottom נקב דק מאד שבמגופת חבית
להוציא ריח היין nekev dak meod shebemigufas chavit lehotzi reiach hayayin
because we make a tiny little air hole for the wine וישוף
שם יקדח שם במקצת ויטעום מן היין. veyashuf sham yekadeiach sham bemiktzat
veyitom min hayayin.
Okay we're afraid that he will maybe in that little air hole
stick some straw in okay. And תוספות Tosfos has a similar like
a different גירסא girsa but essentially the same type of idea. Now
of course if that's true that means that if somehow you were
to do something that were to not have that hole or to
seal that hole or whatever right you would have a way to
totally leave it in the hands of non-Jews if it weren't for
the concern of that tiny little hole. So anyway תוספות Tosfos has
this whole question about well they didn't have this air hole why
did they have to have any concern. So תוספות Tosfos says that
they had wooden barrels and because they had wooden barrels תוספות Tosfos
says that was essentially like this concern of the שייכא sheika because
the wooden barrels you could get like a little knife between the
slats and open it up and you know get a little straw
in or something like that to siphon it off and he said
and that would not be ניכר nikkar and that would not be
מזייף mezayef it would essentially be making a hole that would not
be obvious. So that's why תוספות Tosfos says they also had that
issue but there becomes then this huge תוספות Tosfos about what would
they need to do how big of a סימן siman would they
need to prevent people them getting into those slats or to prevent
them tampering. According to one opinion they'd have to wrap the entire
barrel with like a sackcloth so you couldn't get access to the
barrel and then seal the sack with like a double seal. That
would be the most מחמיר machmir position you know it's like your
airline things which are triple wrapped five different ways and you got
the whole seal. Anyway so that's like one version but תוספות Tosfos
has a lot more lenient possibilities about how to transport wine and
what type of seals and protections they needed to transport them with
non-Jews.
Wine was the main drink there was no sodas no juice it
was a day-to-day also רש"י Rashi says חלים chalim is to solder.
Aha right that's what I meant to get filled right okay yeah
yeah
this is back to why what is This gets back to like
why, what is the aim of them? I mean, it doesn't look
like they can really steal a lot of wine this way. I
mean, it's...
Well, you can siphon it off.
Remember back
in our days, when was it, in the 80s?
Yeah, with the gas.
With the gas?
Yes. So it's enough that they could drink, maybe. Yeah. So you
could get enough to this way with an even tiny...
Right. Now it raises interesting questions which I haven't gotten to. Let's
say they do siphon it off. They didn't touch it. Why is
it אסור? assur? Are we afraid that they'll pour more inferior wine
back in, that is סתם יינם, stam yeinam, whatever? Is the act
of siphoning it off a type of a ניצוק? nitzok? Can that
create a problem? So we haven't really fully fleshed that out either.
Okay.
Right, if you siphon out then pour it back in too.
Right, so if you want to see a little bit of תוספות,
Tosfos,
he says like this. He says, where were we?
Okay, וגם שמנהג העולם, vegam sheminhag ha-olam, so it's about one, two,
three, four, five, six, seven lines from the bottom, right after where
it has a parenthesis, right above where it has a parenthesis שם
דיבור המתחיל דאמר. sham dibbur hamatchil de-amar. So he basically says that
one seal is enough if you'll be able to go back and
look at it. But if you're sending it to somebody you need
two seals. So he
says וגם מנהג העולם היה שכבר vegam minhag ha-olam haya she-kevar was
already for a while the practice לשלוח יין בחותם אחד בלא חוזר
ומכירו lishloach yayin be-chotam echad belo chozer umakiro to be even more
lenient and to assume you don't even have to go back and
look at your own seal. You can send wine to somebody
with one sealed barrel of wine even if you're not going to
be inspecting it later. Okay, ואף אגב דרבא ודאי בעינן הכר חותם
כדפירש בפרק אין מעמידין דאם לאו כן קשיא דרבא אדרבא ve-af agav
de-rava vadai ba-inan haker chotam kidefaresh baperak ein maamidin de-im lav ken
kashya de-rava aderava even though I've been claiming says תוספות Tosfos you
need to be able to go and recognize your seal. מכל מקום
לא קיימא בהכרה אלא קיימא לן כסתמא דתלמודא דשמעתא כדפירש. mikol makom
lo kaimna behankara ela kailan kistama detalmuda deshamaisan kidefaresh. We hold like
our סתם גמרא stam Gemara that one seal totally
suffices. Okay, etc. etc.
Okay, now let's skip a little. He says like
this. Okay, hold on a minute.
Let
me find... I think it was actually earlier where he gave the...
that's the very מיקל meikil read. Hold on, let me find earlier
where he gave... Okay yeah, if you look earlier he says like
this. Three lines before the lines get wide or higher up there
or four lines. אבל רבינו יצחק, Aval Rabbeinu Yitzchak, you see where
it says אבל רבינו יצחק Aval Rabbeinu Yitzchak four lines before it
gets wide, he says like
this. אבל רבינו יצחק בן יהודה שלח לרש״י דוקא לחביות שלהם שהיו
שחורות סגי בחותם אחד Aval Rabbeinu Yitzchak ben Yehuda shalach le-Rashi davka
le-chaviyot shelahem she-hayu shocheres sagi be-chotam echad על פי החבית. al pi
hachavit. אבל בחביות שלנו שהם מנסרים מחוברים aval be-chaviyot shelanu shehem minessarim
mechubarim and they are from planks of wood that are combined זה
לזה, zeh lazeh, אף כי יש חותם אחד על פי החבית af
ki yesh chotam echad al pi hachavit even if there is a
seal, מכל מקום יש לחוש שיתקבוהו עובדי כוכבים בחודו של סכין, mikol
makom yesh lachush she-yitkevuhu ovdei kochavim be-chudo shel sakkin, he'll use the
edge of the knife בין הנסרים או בין השולים ben hanessarim o
ben hashulayim or the base of it
או אפילו באמצע הנסר עצמו o afilu be-emtza hanneser atzmo ולהוציא היין
דרך שם ule-hotzi ha-yayin derech sham ולדחוף על כוס נגד הנקב velidchof
al kos neged hanekev and then use the cup to collect the
wine and right and I guess that's what ומכח כוס הוי ניצוק
חיבור u-makei kusa bitnitzok chibbur etc. because it's collecting in the cup.
Okay, ומיהו, umihu, so that would be the very מחמיר machmir position.
נראה לר״י שאין לחלק בין החביות שלנו לחביות שלהם, Nira le-Ri she-ein
lechalek bein hachaviyot shelanu le-chaviyot shelahem, you shouldn't make that distinction שהרי
לא מצינו שהקפידו התם ואפילו מאן דחייש לסתימה לא חייש לנקובה she-harei
lo matzinu she-hikpidu hatam ve-afilu man de-chaish lestisuma lo chaish lenekiva etc.
etc. So this becomes this big issue about are we worried or
not. Okay and then he goes if just to look let me
show you on עין עמוד א ayin amud alef I'll find you
another מחמיר machmir version of it.
This is the whole thing I said how do you even know
it's the same barrel that was sent if you don't recognize the
barrel.
He says like this.
Okay ומיהו umihu if you look at the top of עין עמוד
א ayin amud alef he says like this.
He says מכל מקום mikol makom to where we left off before
two lines from the top of עין עמוד א. ayin amud alef.
מכל מקום נכון להחמיר לכתחילה, mikol makom nachon lehachmir lachatchila,
it's good לכתחילה lachatchila to not just rely on a simple sealed
barrel. אך בדיעבד אין להפסיד. Ach bedi'avad ein lehafsid. בדיעבד bedi'avad if
somebody sent it with a simple seal it's okay כיון דאיכא חותם
keivan de-ika chotam since it was at least had one seal אפילו
בלא כתב ומכירו afilu belo kesav umakiro even if it wasn't had
Hebrew lettering because Hebrew lettering is something you don't think they can
forge and you don't and the guy who received it doesn't recognize
it. בדיעבד bedi'avad תוספות Tosfos was willing to be very lenient. Any
type of sealed barrel is okay כדפירש. kidefaresh. ומיהו אין
נאה הימנו של חותם אחד מאותיות כי אם מגופתא דטיט כדפירש Umihu
ein naeh mimenu shel chotam echad me-otiyot ki im miguftas tit kidefaresh
but תוספות Tosfos says even in that case it's really not appropriate
to allow a simple sealing of the barrel. Even if you’re not
going to be there to recognize it and you’re going to assume
that our barrels are no worse than their barrels, what you should
do is you should write some Hebrew lettering onto the seal because
that at least is that if the seal were broken, it would
break the letter, and that’s something the non-Jew can’t forge. Okay, so
now you’re seeing what they would do to protect it.
Okay. דמגופת טיט חשיבא חותם אחד אז ודאי אינו מותר בלא כתב
או הכרה. demigufas tit chashiva chosam echad az vadai eino mutar belo
ksav o hachara. That if you just have it sealed and you
don’t—the guy doesn't recognize—who you’re sending it to doesn’t recognize your seal,
and the guy who—and it doesn’t have Hebrew lettering, that really is
a problem even בדיעבד. bedieved. There’s nothing really protecting it in that
case. אלא אם כן ראה השני שנשתלח לו יין קודם לכן עד
שהכלי נתנכר, ela im kein ra'ah hashani shenistalach lo yayin kodem lachen
ad shehakli nisnaker, unless the guy you’re sending it to recognizes the
vessel. ועתה הוא הכיר הכלי בטביעת עין, veata hu hikir hakli betvias
ayin, and he recognizes it now. ואפילו אינו מכיר בחותם לפי שלא
היה חתום באותה שעה, veafilu eino makir bachosam lefi shelo hayah chasum
beosa sha'ah, even if he didn’t recognize the seal; as long—maybe if
he recognizes the vessel. דאם לאו כן, deim lav kein, if he
doesn’t even recognize the vessel: ניהי דלא חיישינן לזיופא, nehi delo chaishinan
leziyufa, even if we’re not afraid that the guy broke the seal,
מכל מקום מנין לנו שהוא אותה חבית של יין? micol makom minayin
lanu shehu osah chavis shel yayin? How do you know he’s delivering
the same barrel of wine altogether ששלח לו חבירו שמא החליף עובד
כוכבים בחבית אחרת
שהיה בו יין במגופה בטיט? sheshalach lo chaveiro shema hechlif oved kochavim
bachavis acheres shehayah bo yayin bemigufa betit? Okay, he won’t break a
seal and reseal it, but maybe he just completely swapped the whole
barrel שגם חביות יין עובדי כוכבים פעמים שמגופם בטיט. shegam chaviyos yayin
ovdei kochavim pe'amim shemigufam betit. Sometimes their barrels are sealed with טיט.
tit. כמו כן צריך, kimo kein tzarich, okay, שניסתם לגמרי הנקב. shenistam
legamrei hanekav. Okay, fine. So it just says, look, even if I’m
not going to demand a double seal and I’m not going to
demand you recognize it and I’m not going to be so afraid
he’s going to forge the seal, at least he’s gotta recognize the
barrel. Okay, and ideally, says תוספות, Tosfos, I’d like there to be
some Hebrew lettering there. Okay. כמו כן צריך שיהא נסתם לגמרי הנקב
קטן שקורין שושפריא בלעז, kimo kein tzarich sheyehei nistam legamrei hanekav katan
shekorin shuspria bila'az, כדאמרינן בתלמודא kidamrinan betalmuda משום שייכא אתא. mishum shaicha
asa. If there’s a little air hole, you gotta seal that, or
else we’re afraid he’s going to stick a tube, a straw through
the air hole. אבל כשהוא חתום באותיות—so aval keshehu chasum be'osyos that’s
in a normal case. You know, minimally he’s gotta recognize the barrel
and the air hole has to be sealed. But better, you should
be using Hebrew
lettering. כשהוא חתום באותיות אין לחוש לכל זה, keshehu chasum be'osyos ein
lachush lechol zeh, דודאי האותיות לא עשו כמי ישראל, devadai ha'osyos lo
asu kemi Yisrael, that the non-Jew doesn’t know how to write Hebrew
lettering. ומכל מקום אין לסמוך המגופה של טיט, umicol makom ein lismoch
hamigufa shel tit, but you shouldn’t rely just on the seal; there
should be lettering. אך נכון הדבר לסתום פי החבית ולתת עור הסתימה
קבוע במסמרות, ach nachon hadavar listom pi hachavis ulatess or hastimah kavua
bemasmeros, but it's best to seal it and then to use leather
to cover it all over. Okay? And to do it with like,
you know, with—and to bang it in with nails so they can’t
get anything between the planks. You know, you have a whole leather
pouch around, you know, the—the planks so that they can’t stick something
between the planks. Okay. ולכתוב אותיות, velichsov osyos, and here’s what you
do: like, you know, when you—like when you ever write a—now it's
all online, but if you remember when you used to write—what do
you call it—letters of reference? You would sign your name on the
back of the envelope, half of your signature, you know, on the—on
the top flap and half on the body, so if it would
be opened and closed, you would see it was opened and closed.
Okay. ולכתוב אותיות חציין על העור וחציין על דופני קרשי החבית, velichsov
osyos chatzyan al ha'or vechatzyan al dofnei karshei hachavis, שאם יגביה עובד
כוכבים העור, sheim yagbiya oved kochavim ha'or, if he tries to lift
up the leather, לא ידע ידו לישבו כבראשונה. lo yeida yado leyashvo
kevarishona. He won’t be able to realign it the way it was
before. So you gotta cover it with this leather and you use
this Hebrew—with this leather and you use this Hebrew lettering. ולתת חשוק
שקורין צרקלא סביב העגולים במקום שמחוברים על דופני החבית, velatess chashuk shekorin
tzarkla saviv ha'igulim bemakom shemechubarim al dofnei hachavis, and to put some
type of like a metal bands or belts around it to keep
the leather there. Okay, etc., etc., etc. Okay, so all these other
ways in which to prevent him from getting access into the wine.
Okay, and so now he goes into this long, strict thing. So
he goes from being extremely lenient. Okay, yeah, it’s all the same,
our barrels, their barrels, we don’t worry that ours are wood, one
חותם chosam is enough even if he doesn’t recognize it, to like
this other complete extreme, that you gotta wrap it with leather and
do it—do the lettering and do the whole thing in all these
positions in the middle. So there you go, trying to—תוספות Tosfos trying
to sort of figure out based on this גמרא Gemara and based
on their realities what was needed to protect the wine from being,
you know, swapped or mishandled. Okay, let's go back to the גמרא
Gemara and read a little bit more. We pointed out that our
משנה Mishnah was interesting that they discussed a scenario of a Jew
and a non-Jew at a table drinking wine together. It sounded even
like the non-Jew was pouring the wine or whatever, which is bizarre,
but anyway, maybe only once the Jew left. Now listen to this
scenario. אמר רבא זונה עובדת כוכבים וישראל מסובין אצלה. Amar Rava zona
ovedes kochavim veYisrael mesubin etzlah. So a Jew has hired—they don’t just
happen to be eating at the same table. This is—I don’t know
if this is also maybe a little bit of a—of a—of a—of
a poke at like the stories with Jesus who would eat with
the tax collectors and the prostitutes, which is exactly that, you know,
whatever, you know, that was also—Jesus was obviously trying to poke at
the whole rabbinic hierarchy and, you know, whatever, caste sort of system
or class system. Anyway, so there’s this Jew who's hired the services
of a prostitute and she's she's at his house and they're eating
at the table and they're drinking wine. Okay, חמר שרי. chamar shari.
You we are not afraid that she touched the wine and if
somebody now wants to go I mean to this Jew wants to
know, you know, if he can drink the wine. He's not afraid
of the about about using the services of a prostitute, but he
doesn't want to drink the non-kosher wine or somebody wants to have
his wine and knows that he did this or whatever, you don't
have to be afraid that just 'cause he's violating this law and
have and you know, using the services of a prostitute, that he's
not going to be careful with כשרות. kashrus. Sadly we very well
know that this is how sometimes how people act. Okay, anyway, it's
חמר שרי, chamar shari, the wine is permissible. נהי דתקיף ליה יצרא
דעבירה, nehi detakif leh yitzra de'aveira, maybe he's got a יצר הרע
yeitzer hara for עבירה, aveira, which often means specifically and in this
case it does, for sexual sin. Okay, and he's violating in that
regard. יצרא דיין נסך לא תקיף ליה. yitzra deyayin nesech lo takif
leh. Okay, so, you know, he is not it's just 'cause he's
going to violate and sin with her sexually, doesn't mean that he's
going to go ahead and like, you know, pour the wine for
עבודה זרה avodah zarah and he's not going to necessarily give her
license to handle the wine, etc.
However, if it were the reverse, זונה ישראלית ועובדי כוכבים מסובין, zonah
yisre'elit ve'ovdei kochavim mesubin, let's say a Jewish prostitute was hiring herself
out to a non-Jewish man, okay, מסובין, mesubin, חמרא אסיר. chamra asir.
The wine is forbidden. Okay, presumably even her wine is forbidden, okay,
and you're afraid he touched it. Why? הואיל וזילה עלייהו, ho'il vezila
aleihu, since she is like, you know, she's making herself sort of
like available to him, like lowly to him, you know, she's not
she's not standing on her own dignity. So in that case, בתרייהו
גרירא, batraihu grira, she'll just follow after him. So either that means
that either she'll use the wine for עבודה זרה avodah zarah or
she'll let him handle the wine. Okay, so basically the assumption here
being that if the man is the one hiring the services of
the prostitute, it's the man who determines. So if the man is
Jewish, you assume the wine remains okay, okay, and just 'cause he's
doing this one sin, you don't assume he's doing this other sin
and you assume he didn't I guess let her touch the wine.
And if the man is not Jewish, then even if it's her
wine, you assume that since he's hiring her services or whatever, you
know, that he's now handling the wine as well and that the
wine is forbidden. All right, so I guess we will end with
that and that lovely point.